Guide to the New York State National Guard, 9th Regiment Collection 1812-1961 MS 3085
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV: Collected Documents, 1814-1961; 2.79 Linear feet
  - Petition from the 9th Regiment (83rd Regiment N.Y. Volunteers) (1 of 2), 1863 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
    This folder holds a photocopy of a petition from the officers and rank and file of the 9th Regiment to Brigadier General Thomas requesting to be mustered out of service. It was signed by the Officers, Non-commissioned officers, and men of the 9th Regiment N.Y.S.M. (83rd Regiment N.Y. Volunteers) on May 22nd 1863.
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access to the original document is restricted because of its fragility. Please use this photocopy instead. Requests to use the original need to be approved by the Curator of Manuscripts.
  - Petition from the 9th Regiment (83rd Regiment N.Y. Volunteers) (2 of 2), 1863 (Offsite-box 11)
    This box holds the original petition noted above. Please use the photocopy in box 4. Requests to use the original must be approved by the Curator of Manuscripts because of the item's fragility. The document received conservation treatment in August 2019 by Assistant Conservator Katarzyna Bator.
  - Welcome Home Banquet (83rd NY Volunteers), 1864, 1901 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
    Folder contains a ribbon, invitation card, menu, poems, and a resolution.
  - Regiment Descriptive Book, 1860s (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
    The volume lists names of field and staff officers, non-commissioned officers, commissioned line officers, and rank and file soldiers by company. Indicates date commissioned or mustered in, and remarks on deaths, deserters, promotions, expulsions, or other termination of service. Entries appear to begin circa 1864 (possibly just after the regiment was mustered out of service as the 83rd Volunteers), though there are references to men who mustered in earlier. Entries appear to end circa 1868.
  - Life of Major Charles Steelhammer, Co. B, 9th NYSM (83rd NY Volunteers), circa 1912 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16a)
    This folder contains a typed biography/obituary of Major Steelhammer, including his Civil War service with the 9th.
  - Captain Peter J. Martin, 1861, 1869 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
    two certificates: appointment to sergeant in Company F of the 9th Regiment and resignation from the 1st Regiment, NYSNG.
  - Minutes "B" Company.(flat box), 1864 November-1866 October (Offsite-box 10)
  - 3rd Brigade N.Y. State Militia National Guard Co. B Roll, 1864-1871 (Folder OS-Medium)
    Parchment roll listing signatures of enlisted men, dates of signature, and home addresses. The men who signed this roll were agreeing to seven years of military service and upon completion of their service, they would be discharged and given a lifetime of jury duty.
  - Career of Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock (Folder 1 of 2), 1871-1878, 1924 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings, general orders, oaths of office, NRA membership tickets, portrait/engraving, an obituary/military record, and correspondence from 7th Regiment. There are documents relating to the Orange Riot (1871), Albany Riot (1877), and news coverage of Hitchcock's death (1878). See Folder 2 for oversized items. See also the Scrapbook series.
  - Career of Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock, (Folder 2 of 2) (flat box), 1872, 1875 (Offsite-box 10)
    Certificates of appointment as Lt. Colonel and as Colonel.
  - Colonel James Fisk Jr., 1870-1871 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
    This folder contains tickets to the 9th Regiment Ball, engraved portrait of Fisk, "Ninth Regiment Quick Step" sheet music, and a newspaper article from the Evening Telegram detailing a play about Jim Fisk.
  - 9th Regiment Bayonet Drill, 1882 April (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    Centerfold in Harper's Weekly depicting bayonet drills practiced by the 9th Regiment.
  - Colonel Solomon E. Japha (service 1871-1912) (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    This folder contains copies of military orders, newspaper clippings, enlistment papers, a Private's certificate of membership, and photographs.
  - Sergeant Henry A. Harris (service 1877-1917), 1877-1937 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    This folder contains applications for a certificate in lieu of lost or destroyed discharge certificate, special orders, correspondence, official military paperwork, discharge certificate, photographs, and a photograph of his medals. Harris served in Spanish American War.
  - Sergeant Frederick Kramer (2 folders), 1879-1915 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22a, b)
    These folders contains 12 photographs (Kramer, comrades), as well as various promotion certificates and honorable discharge papers.
  - John A. Dix Post 135 / Grand Army of the Republic, 1885-1938 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
    This folder contains general orders, invitations, newspaper clippings, poems, G.A.R booklets, notes on deaths in Confederate state prisons (1861-1865), and a GAR Kings County linen American flag.
  - Veterans of the Ninth Regiment Bound Resolution, 1886 June (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
    Bound resolution from the Veterans of the Ninth to the Board of Officers of the Ninth Regiment, concerning the parade on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the regiment's departure for the Civil War.
  - 9th Regiment Gettysburg Monument, 1887-1888 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    This folder contains a program for the "Grand Benefit Performance" for the 9th Regiment memorial fund and a program for the oration of the Hon. Orlando B Potter on the dedication of the Gettysburg monument.
  - "Infantry Drill Regulations", 1891 October (Offsite-box 4, Folder 26)
    Publication of the U.S. War Department. the booklet provides an overview on topics such as: military terminology, tactics, fire discipline, and trumpet calls. Booklet belonged to James Thomas Madden, Lieutenant, 9th Regiment, N.G.S.N.Y.
  - Sergeant Ephraim Japha, 1894-1938 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 27)
    This folder contains several photographs (most with groups of soldiers), membership card for the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment Association, certificate of membership, copy of general orders, military promotion certificates, and programs and notices from the Veterans Association (from the 1930s, when Ranlet was an officer).
  - First Sergeant Daniel M. Ranlet (2 folders), 1895-1938 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 28a, b)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings, official military documents (Spanish Campaign 1898), photographs of Company B, drawings, correspondence, military orders, and papers from the Veterans of the Ninth Regiment.
  - Orders from Headquarters, 9th Regiment, First Brigade, 1887, 1894-1900 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 29)
    The orders contained in this folder were collected by Colonel D.M. Ranlet.
  - Muster Roll and Payroll, Company B, 1898 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 30)
  - Muster Out Roll, Company A. (flat box), 1898 (Offsite-box 10)
  - Spanish-American War, 1898-1899, 1947 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
    This folder contains a list of deaths, veteran card, official/military correspondence, circulars from United Spanish War Veterans, register of the commanding officers of the 9th Regiment Infantry New York Volunteers in the Spanish-American War, and enlistment ID cards for some soldiers.
  - Spanish-American War Photographs. (flat box ), 1898 (Offsite-box 10)
    Three photographs of the 9th Regiment at Camp Townsend in Peekskill, NY. There is a list of the entire regiment on the back of the group photograph.
  - Invitations and Programs, 1866-1958 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 32)
    These invitations and programs are for events hosted by the Ninth Regiment, including bayonet drill (1882), minstrel entertainment (1894), dinners, reviews, opening of the new armory on 14th street (1897), ranging from the mid-19th to mid-20th centuries.
  - Invitations and Programs, 1873-1954 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 33)
    These invitations and programs are for events hosted by the Veterans of the 9th Regiment, including dinners, memorial services, reunions, and pilgrimages.
  - Athletic Events, 1885-1943 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 34)
    This folder contains five programs for athletic events hosted by the 9th Regiment.
  - Historical Notes 19th Century, circa 1888-1949 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 35)
    This folder contains compiled papers, transcripts and notes relating primarily to the 19th century history of the 9th Regiment. Documents include, among others: the Address of Lt. Col. Simon Fleet (Dec 15, 1812), a petition of Veterans of the 9th Regiment for New Armory (Jan 9, 1889), notes on 9th Regiment council of admin (1800-1823), circulars, newspaper clippings, handwritten notes, papers relating to the unveiling of Gettysburg monument, typed notes, and a newspaper centerfold from 1949 about the death of James Fisk.
  - 19th Century New York State Riots, 1907? (Offsite-box 4, Folder 36)
    This folder contains lists and other documents discussing the 9th Regiment's role with 19th Century riots in New York state. The information appears to have been compiled in 1907.
  - Veterans Association Bulletins and Notices, 1886-1938 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1890s-1905 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 38)
    This folder contains three photographs: portrait of William Todd (editor of history of the 9th Regiment, 83rd NY Volunteers), portrait of Mayor FW Ward (9th Coast Artillery), and portrait of Governor Odell and staff (1905).
  - Dedication of Regiment Tablet at University Place and 13th Street, 1908 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 39)
    This folder contains circulars and a draft speech.
  - Photographs of NCO Staff at Fort Wadsworth, 1908-1910 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 40)
    This folder contains three photographs.
  - Library Catalog?, circa 1905 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
  - World War I, 1917-1919 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    This folder contains: Captain AJ McGrath's individual pay book; a list of battles the 9th regiment participated in; a permanent pass; a war songs booklet; "First Battalion 57th Artillery C.A.C. in the First World War" book; Service in the WW Roster 13th Co, 9th N.Y.C.D.C.N.G.U.S. Fort Hancock NJ circular; a sketch of Battery "D", 57th Artillery CAC; poems; a circular from the Commander of the American Expeditionary Forces John Pershing; newspaper clippings; and telegram.
  - 9th Coast Artillery Corps. (N.Y.G.), 1917-1919 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    This folder contains papers relating to the 9th Coast Artillery Corps N.Y.G. (Veterans Corps of Artillery). Documents include: mess ticket, history and list of officers/men of the Ninth Coast Artillery N.Y.G., newspaper clipping, advert for welcome home ceremony, Society of the War of 1812 and the Veterans Corps of Artillery pamphlet, and the By-Laws of the Officers Association of the 9th Coast Artillery N.Y.G booklet.
  - Letters to Major Mills Miller from France (WWI), 1917-1918 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    This folder contains four letters sent to Major Mills Miller who was stationed at Sandy Hook, NJ.
  - Lieutenant Louis W. Chapin (VCH-9 CHC 244), 1917-1940 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    This folder contains: military rosters, War Department/Militia Bureau correspondence, a discharge certificate, nomination paperwork, special orders, decoration paperwork, review pamphlets, extension courses notes, and certificates.
  - Miscellaneous Photographs 9th Regiment, 1921-1936 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    This folder contains five photographs and two newspaper clippings.
  - Colonel John J. Byrne, 1901, 1915-1941 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    This folder contains papers and photographs relating to Colonel John J. Byrne. Content of folder includes: photographs (including the Coast Artillery Brigade on parade on Army Day, April 2, 1932), correspondence, newspaper clippings about Byrne's funeral, an IRS Tax Exemption document and other documents related to the estate of Byrne, program for dinner in honor of Brigadier General John J. Byrne (retirement party), and reunion invitations.
  - The Russian Battery, 1932, 1934, 1961 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    This folder contains papers relating to the Russian Battery (2nd Combat Train - 244th Coastal Artillery). Documents include: a postcard from Ft. Ontario, an obituary for Colonel Peter Rodyenko, and a program for the 5th Anniversary Russian Battery.
  - First Lieutenant Edward P. Anderson, 1937 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
    This folder contains a commission certificate.
  - Officers' Association, 9th Coast Artillery Corps Meeting Minutes (2 folders), 1873, 1917-1939 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - 244th Coastal Artillery and Camp Pendleton, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    The contents of this folder relate to the 244th Coastal Artillery's assignment to Camp Pendleton, VA. Documents include: General orders, a circular proposing a trip to Virginia Beach, memo to Historian of the 9th Regiment including patches, as well as a roster of organization name, vehicle type, vehicle number, driver, permit number, and assistant driver.
    It should be noted that the roster was removed from its original metal binding and grouped together.
  - Constitutions and Certificates for the Veterans of the Ninth, 1919-1941 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
    This folder contains photocopies of the constitutions for the Veterans of the 9th Regiment, a typed draft of the preamble to the constitution, a typed draft of removals/expulsions, typed constitution and by laws of Veterans of the Ninth Regiment, and various updated versions of the constitution.
  - Historical Notes, 1908-1941 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
    This folder contains a 1941 document that gives a summary of the history of the 9th Regiment; a list prepared in 1908 of commandants from 1799-1899; and a note concerning the continuity of the regiment's history (1933).
  - Organizational History 633d AAA AW Bn, 1942-1945 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper and Newsletters (WWII), 1940-1945 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings and newsletters relating to the 9th Regiment (244th, 633rd).
  - History of the 1st Battalion 244th CA/633rd AAA Europe (WWII) (Folder 1 of 2), 1943-1945 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 17)
    This folder contains: "The Story of the 80th Infantry Division" booklet, photographs, a roster of officers + addresses, instruction manual "Service of the Piece 40 mm Antiaircraft Gun," Training Memorandum - Fire Control - Stiffkey Stick and Eyeshooting, and a copy of a message stating German surrender. See Folder 2 for oversized content.
  - History of the 1st Battalion 244th CA/633rd AAA Europe (WWII), Oversized (Folder 2 of 2), 1945 (Folder OS-Medium)
    Map entitled "Blue Ridge Path through France, Luxembourg, Germany, and Austria" and a poster with army insignias.
  - S-3 Journal 633rd AAA AW Battalion, 1944 June-1945 February (Offsite-box 5, Folder 18)
    The contents of this folder were removed from their original metal binding.
  - Awards to Members of the 633rd AAA AW Battalion, 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 19)
  - Unit Commendations of 633 AAA AW Battalion, 1944-1945 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 20)
    This folder contains paperwork describing the commendations.
  - New York Guard - World War II (Folder 1 of 2), 1940-1947 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 21)
    This folder contains: a letter containing a 10 Yen bill with blood stain, photographs, program for "Spanish War Veterans Night," program/menu for the 9th Regiment N.Y. Guard Board of Officers Dinner-Dance, program for the review and presentation of enrollment awards, program for memorial services, and a N.Y. Guard sleeping mask.
    See Folder 2 for oversized content.
  - New York Guard - World War II (Folder 2 of 2)., Oversized, 1944 (Folder OS-Medium)
    Map of Camp Smith (Peekskill, NY)
  - Lieutenant Colonel John C. Mazzei, 1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 22)
    This folder contains correspondence and articles written by LTC John C. Mazzei.
  - History of 2nd Battalion 244th Coastal Artillery Aleutian Islands (WWII), 1941,1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 23)
    This folder contains a typed transcript of battalion diary and a reprint of newspaper clipping about 9th Regiment post-Aleutian Islands.
  - History of 3rd Battalion 244th Coastal Artillery Guadalcanal (WWII), 1943-1944 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 24)
    This folder contains: a report, newspaper clipping, Christmas program from the Fiji Islands, photocopies of communiques from the Secretary of the Navy, and photographs.
  - World War II, 1940-1945 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 25)
    This folder contains: a memo about the regiment's history, general orders, documents relating to Comrade Cammarano, War Department papers/memos, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and Christmas cards.
  - Korean War, 1950-1951 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 26)
    The documents in this folder relate to the 633rd and 259th's mobilization into Federal service in preparation for deployment in Korea. The contents of this folder include official military documents and a newspaper clipping.
  - Orders HQ 244th AAA Group, 1953-1956 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 27)
    This folder contains: information bulletins, reports about deceased, special orders, and map summaries.
  - Officers and Warrant Officers of 244th AAA Group NYG, 1957 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
    This folder contains a photograph of the many commanders and warrant officers of the 244th AAA Group NYG.
- Series V: Photograph Albums, 1861-1945; 1.65 Linear feet
  The photo albums in this series span from the Civil War to World War II. They contain group photographs, headshots of commanders/NCOs/enlisted men, training photographs, candid snapshots, aerial photographs, as well as pictures taken at specific camps and forts.
  The photograph albums are mainly arranged by military conflict, and when possible, chronologically.
  - "War of the Rebellion" Photo Album 1, 1861-1865 (Offsite-box 6)
    This photo album of cartes-de-visite is entitled "Commissioned Officers and Non-Commissioned Officers of the 9th N.Y.S.M (83rd N.Y. Vols.) who served in the War of the Rebellion, 1861-1865." Photo albums focuses upon Staff Officers, Field Officers, as well as company officers.
  - "War of the Rebellion" Photo Album 2, 1861-1865 (Offsite-box 6)
    This photo album of cartes-de-visite is entitled "Officers and Enlisted Men of the 9th N.Y.S.M (83rd N.Y. Vols.) who served in the War of the Rebellion, 1861-1865." Photographs focus on Company A, B C, and D.
  - "War of the Rebellion" Photo Album 3, 1861-1865 (Offsite-box 6)
    This photo album of cartes-de-visite is entitled "Officers and Enlisted Men of the 9th N.Y.S.M (83rd N.Y. Vols.) who served in the War of the Rebellion, 1861-1865." Photographs focus upon Company E, F, and G.
  - "War of the Rebellion" Photo Album 4, 1861-1865 (Offsite-box 6)
    This photo album of cartes-de-visite is entitled "Officers and Enlisted Men of the 9th N.Y.S.M (83rd N.Y. Vols.) who served in the War of the Rebellion, 1861-1865." Photographs focus upon Company H, I, and L.
  - Commissioned Officers of the Spanish-American War, 1898 (Offsite-box 6)
    Photo album, mostly of cabinet cards, entitled "Commissioned Officers of the Ninth Regiment N.Y., N.Y. - 9th Infantry N.Y. Vols. who served in the Spanish-American War. May 2nd - Nov. 15, 1898."
  - Ninth Regiment Veteran Corps., 1871-1906 (Offsite-box 6)
    Photo album entitled "Members of the Ninth Regiment Veterans Corps., 83rd N.Y. Vols (1861-1865), 9th N.Y. Vols. (1898), May 27th, 1900" and consists of professional head shots, mostly cabinet cards.
  - 9th Regiment Photo Album, 1917-1939 (Offsite-box 7)
    This photo album contains photographs of the 9th Regiment in Peekskill, NY (1917), Fisher's Island (1921-1923), candid snapshots, military training photographs, pictures of the regiment's encampment, unit/group shots, ship photographs, Niagara Falls (1925), Fort Ontario (1925-1939), and more.
  - 9th Regiment NYG Camp Smith, 1945 (Offsite-box 10)
    This photo album contains group photographs (officers, NCOs, social organizations, companies), aerial photographs of the area surrounding Camp Smith, and training photographs.
- Series VI: Scrapbooks, 1812-1950; 3.44 Linear feet
  This series contains scrapbooks filled with newspaper clippings, typescripts of historical documents, ephemera, and more about the regiment. Two scrapbooks focus upon the life and career of Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock.
  The "Press Campfire and GAR" scrapbook and "Death of Colonel J.R. Hitchcock" have been placed into folders and housed in record carton. The 9th Regiment scrapbook has been placed in an oversized folder, whilst the Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock Memorial scrapbook is contained in its own document box.
  - Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock Memorial Scrapbook, 1878 (Offsite-box 8)
    Book memorializing the life and career of Colonel James Roosevelt Hitchcock. The pages are thick, almost wood-like.
  - Death of Colonel J.R. Hitchcock Scrapbook, 1878 (Offsite-box 10)
    Scrapbook filled with newspaper clippings related to the death of Colonel J.R. Hitchcock.
  - The Press Campfire & GAR Scrapbook, 1898-1901 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29)
    Grand Army of the Republic scrapbook filled with newspaper clippings of newspaper column "the Press Campfire."
  - 9th Regiment Scrapbook (1799-1917), 1812-1950 (Offsite-box 9)
    Scrapbook filled with newspaper clippings, typescripts of historical documents, invitations, ephemera, and more. It should be noted that the majority of the scrapbook focuses upon 1799-1917, however there are some documents from the 1940s-1950s. The earliest original documents are two orders dating from 1812 and 1814. Other original documents date from the late 1860s and after.